<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the Cathedral of St. Peters in York on the fifth day of Novemb. 1689 by William Perse ...</title>
            <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1654</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7086</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12588044</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12588044</idno>
            <idno type="VID">63799</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 63799)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 674:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the Cathedral of St. Peters in York on the fifth day of Novemb. 1689 by William Perse ...</title>
                  <author>Perse, William, 1640 or 41-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 41 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Bulkley for Francis Hildyard ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>York [England] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXIX, 1-2 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:63799:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the <hi>CATHEDRAL</hi> OF <hi>St Peters in York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>Fifth</hi> day of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> William Perſe, <hi>M.A. Rector of Weſt</hi> Heſlerton, <hi>and Chaplain to the Right Honourable</hi> Lewis <hi>Earle of</hi> Feverſham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> Charles Palmer, <hi>R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. in Chriſto Patri, ac D<hi rend="sup">no</hi>. D<hi rend="sup">no</hi>.</hi> Thomae <hi>Archiep.</hi> Ebor. à Sacris Domeſticis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>York,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Bulkley</hi> for <hi>Francis Hildyard</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Stonegate.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:63799:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:63799:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 129.1.2.</hi> Verſes,</bibl>
                  <p>Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth may Iſrael now ſay:</p>
                  <p>Many a time have they afflicted me from my youth; yet they have not prevailed againſt me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt the many undeniable and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable arguments that may be brought to prove the Exiſtence of God, the conſideration of the great Care which He the Supreme Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and Moderator of all things hath in all Ages taken to preſerve his ſmall Flock, <hi>the Church,</hi> from the Paw of the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Beare;</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the Arts and Stratagems, all the force and cunning of her potent and vigilant Adverſaries) ſeems to me not to be of the leaſt moment to convince an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> of his impiety, a <hi>Pagan</hi> of his Infidelity, an <hi>Heretick</hi> of his Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, and a <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> of his dangerous and erroneous Opinions. For ſurely were there not a God in heaven that put a ſtop not only to the raging of the Sea, but the madneſs of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:63799:3"/>were there not a God who ſet Limits to the Waves, and bounds to the fury of Tyrannical Oppreſſors; were there not a God who put a Hook into the Jaws of the great <hi>Leviathans:</hi> the ſpiritual Church had long ſince been like ſome of the material Churches in the low Countreys, quite under water: The Floods of Oppreſſion had overflown her, and ſhe had long ere this become a prey to thoſe many Enemies which even from her infancy have Watch'd and Waited for her ruin and deſtruction. To ſee the Church like the <hi>Salamander,</hi> not only living in the fire of Afflictions but as it were receiving nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment from the inoffenſive Flames; to ſee the Holy Buſh-burning without any detriment to its own ſubſtance, is a ſufficient Argument that there is an Angel that Protects her, an inviſible pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that dwells within her, which preſerves her body from ſcorching, though not always her Garments, her <hi>external Conſtitutions</hi> from the ſmell of the Fire: That ſuch a ſmall Veſſel as the Church ſhould Ride out ſo many bluſtring ſtorms on a troubleſome and tempeſtuous Sea, without bulging or leaking, without ſplitting on the Shelves, or being ſwallowed up of the Sands, muſt needs proceed from the skill and care of her indefatigable Pilot, and the ſtrength of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:63799:3"/>and irremovable Anchor: for what the Diſciples ſaid to Jeſus when a ſudden guſt of Wind aroſe on the Lake, and filled the Ship with Water, <hi>Help Maſter or we periſh,</hi> is moſt true of the Church in general: Were it not for his aid and aſſiſtance, for his continual preſence, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Commands, whom the Winds and Sea, and all boyſtrous and otherwiſe unruly paſſions obey, we ſhould not only be toſt to and fro with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wind of uncertain Doctrine and ſo become unſetled in our Judgements, and Reſolutions, but alſo we ſhould ſuffer on the one ſide from Pira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Oppreſſors, and on the other from Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Schiſmatical Intruders.</p>
            <p>It had been impoſſible for Chriſtianity, like <hi>Rome</hi> now the great Oppoſer of it, which from a few ſcattered Cottages came to be the ſoveraign Commandreſs of the whole known World, to have ſtretched out her Empire ſo far, and wide as it is at this day, and that from ſo low and ſmall beginnings, had not the Divine Spirit car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her on and protected her, aſſiſted and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held her in ſpight of all oppoſition, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction whatſoever: Turning ſome unto that Faith which they but lately perſecuted, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the wicked deſigns and machinations of others, and confounding all their devices; ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:63799:4"/>that diverſe convers'd with <hi>Lyens</hi> without and danger, and play'd upon the hole of the <hi>Aſp,</hi> and the Den of the <hi>Cockatrice</hi> in great ſecurity, as was foretold by the Prophet concerning the firſt days of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> God hath built his Church upon a Mountain that cannot be ſhaken, on a Rock that cannot be moved; for though the rain deſcend, the Winds blow, and the Floods riſe, though the Rain of adverſity may wet her, and the Floods of perſecution may rage againſt her, and the furious blaſts of diſcord and diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may ruffle and diſcompoſe her outward Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet the Church her ſelf ſhall not fall, nor her Faith totally fail, nor even the Gates of Hell prevail againſt her; for ſhe is founded upon a Rock, even the Rock Chriſt Jeſus: he is her Saviour and deliverer, her Fortreſs and Caſtle of defence, under the ſhadow of whoſe Wings, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the coverture of whoſe gracious providence ſhe ſhall be ſafe and ſecure till all Tyranny and Oppreſſion, all rage and violence, all Envy and Malice be quite paſt and blown over: For though they have afflicted her from her youth may <hi>Iſrael</hi> now ſay, <hi>though many a time have they afflicted her from her youth, yet have they not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt her.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:63799:4"/>
            <p>From which Declaration of the royal <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt</hi> we may obſerve.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The inveterate Malice, and the unwearied Induſtry of the men of this world to ruine <hi>Sion,</hi> and to pull down the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time have they afflicted her from her youth,</hi> many a time will they afflict her in her old age.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Fruſtration of their deſign, or the ill ſucceſs that all thoſe meet with who ſtrive to oppoſe the Truth by Violence, or to detain it in ungodlineſs by Fraud. <hi>Yet have they not prevailed againſt me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Retribution or return that the Church is bound to make, <hi>Deo ſtatori &amp; liberatori,</hi> to her Saviour and Deliverer, for the preſervation of her ſelf and the deſtruction of her Enemies. <hi>May Iſrael now ſay,</hi> ought <hi>Iſrael</hi> now to ſay.</p>
            <p>The frequent Declarations of the Mercies and Deliverances we receive from the hand of God; is a ſign of the value and eſtimation we put upon them, and the ready way to increaſe their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. The Remembrance of the Churches danger and of her wonderful deliverance from it muſt be the burden of her Song of Thankſgiving: For ſo the ingemmation of my Text, as in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſeems to import.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:63799:5"/>
            <p>In the firſt general Obſervation we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider 1. Who they are that are ſo malicious as to envy the peace of <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſo ſedulous and diligent in contriving her Deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How frequent they are in their Attempts.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By what ways and means they indeavour to bring their wicked and pernicious deſigns to paſs.</p>
            <p>And this I ſhall ſhow in the Phraſe and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of my Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> are many. Their multitude renders them formidable: <hi>Illos defendit Numerus junctaeque Umbone Phalanges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Many a time do they renew their Aſſaults; Like importunate Beggars one or two denials will not ſhake them off; one or two, or twenty diſappointments do not diſhearten or cauſe them to deſiſt from their interprize: This but whets their anger and inventions: <hi>Animos a vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere ſumunt:</hi> Like <hi>Antaeus</hi> they ſeem to receive vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour from their very falls. This ſhows their Obſtinacy and inveteracy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They have many ways to execute their Fury and to bring their hidden purpoſes to perfection. The Sword and the Mattock. open Force, and hidden Treachery: I might put in the Pen like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:63799:5"/>none of the leaſt invenom'd Weapons they make uſe of to accompliſh their wicked deſigns: Beſides a thouſand little Arts they have to delude the Vulgar, and to hold ſilly ignorant people Captive this ſhows their Cunning. They do as <hi>Balaam</hi> did, at the requeſt of <hi>Balak;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 23.13</note> if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> from one Hill, they will try a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and another after that, to ſee if at length ſome one lucky hit may render their Faſcinations and Enchantments proſperous and ſucceſsful.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Enemies of the <hi>Church</hi> are many; Too many for me to ſpeak to within the compaſs allotted for this Exerciſe; too many for the poor Church by her own ſtrength to encounter, but not too many for her Almighty Patron and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Champion to deliver her from: For though all the Legions of Darkneſs ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine in one againſt her, and call in all their Auxiliaries to their aſſiſtance, all thoſe who for the Virulency of their Principles, and the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of their practice, may be ſtil'd Devils incarnate, yet ſhould they be as chaffe before the wind, and the Angel of the Lord ſcattering them, as the fire burneth the Wood, and the flame conſumeth the Mountains, ſo ſhall God perſecute them with his Tempeſt and make them afraid with his Storm. Though they come about
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:63799:6"/>her like <hi>Bees</hi> yet ſhall they be extinct as the fire amongſt Thorns, ſo ſuddenly ſhall they vaniſh and be no more. Though the Red Dragon open his mouth wide to devour her and her offspring, yet God will prepare a place-in the Wilderneſs for them to retire unto: And though he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her thither, yet he ſhall give her the wings of an <hi>Eagle</hi> that ſhe may fly away and be at reſt: and though the <hi>Serpent</hi> caſt whole Floods of Water out of his mouth to overwhelm her, yet the Earth ſhall preſerve her, by receiving them into her large and vaſt Treaſury As the <hi>Air</hi> before, ſo the <hi>Earth</hi> now, yea even all <hi>Elements</hi> ſhall by the direction and command of their Superior Agent, contribute to her ſecurity, and preſervation. The Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: She may well ſay as <hi>David</hi> did in her perſon, <hi>All nations have compaſſed me about, they have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted together with one conſent, and are confederate againſt me; the Tabernacles of</hi> Edom, <hi>and the Iſhmaelites of</hi> Moab, <hi>and the</hi> Hagaerens, thoſe indeed who to our great trouble, (and the greater, becauſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by one who calls himſelf <hi>the moſt Chriſtian King,</hi>) have overſpread a conſiderable part of the once Chriſtian <hi>Empire;</hi> Though the late proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſucceſſes of the Churches Arms make us to hope, that notwithſtanding thoſe indirect and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:63799:6"/>unchriſtian practices, their late Half Moon is haſtily declining to its utmoſt Waine. <hi>Gebal</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalek,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with the inhabitants of <hi>Tyre, Aſſur,</hi> alſo is joyned with them and have holpen the Children of <hi>Lot.</hi> The Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> you ſee are many: The <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> which God hath planted for himſelf with his own right hand is infeſted, and troubled with many Adverſaries that envy her Felicity, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour her utter extirpation. There are wild <hi>Boares</hi> that break down her Hedges, and would lay her open, and make her common to the Beaſts of the Wide, and unmanured Wilderneſs: And there are little <hi>Foxes</hi> that creep through them and crop her tender Budds: There are Sacrilegious <hi>Caterpillars</hi> that devour her faireſt Cluſters, her beſt and richeſt poſſeſſions: And there are <hi>Tere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines</hi> little Creatures that worm themſelves into the body of the <hi>Vine,</hi> and corrupt it, and others that gnaw at the very Root thinking to kill, and deſtroy it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall paſſe by her Forreign Adverſaries, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,</hi> and Infidells who deny the very Principles and firſt Grounds of our moſt excellent Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whoſe Eyes the God of this World hath ſo blinded that they cannot ſee the wonders of Gods Law: and come to ſome of her domeſtick and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:63799:7"/>homebred Foes, thoſe that eat of her Bread and drink of her Cup, that partake of the ſame Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, Communicate of the ſame Sacraments, that acknowledge the ſame faith, and yet either out of Pride or Ignorance, Folly or Conrempt lift up their heel againſt her.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some of thoſe many Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> that moleſt and diſturb her are thoſe who joyning with her in her outward worſhip, in the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of her excellent Diſcipline, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of her ſound and Orthodox Doctrine, do notwithſtanding to their own ſhame, and the Churches prejudice depart from her in their practice, and manner of outward converſation: whoſe lives are no ways anſwerable to that moſt holy Religion which they profeſs. <hi>Qui aliud, aiunt, aliud vivunt.</hi> That ſpeak the words of <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> and live the life of <hi>Simon Magnus.</hi> And truly theſe are none of the leaſt Enemies that the Church of Chriſt hath; for there are no wounds like the wounds of a Friend, they ſtrike deepeſt and are moſt unkindly reſented. Such as theſe give advantage to the Gainſayers of the Truth, and make them ſpeak evil of that moſt innocent Goſpel that is firſt pure, and then peaceable. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I hear our bleſſed Saviour ſaying to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:63799:7"/>ſinning Chriſtian that lives indirect oppoſition to thoſe divine Precepts which he left to be the Rule and Guide of our Actions, ſomething not unlike what the chaſt and dying <hi>Arria</hi> ſaid to her beloved <hi>Paetus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Vulnus Iudaeus quod fecit non dolet inquit;</l>
               <l>Sed quod tu facies hoc, mihi crede dolet.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Wounds that the malicious and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirſty <hi>Jews</hi> made in my Hands my Feet do not trouble me being they were given me for thy ſake do procure an Attonement for thee: but they are thoſe which thou my Friend and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion whom I loved as my ſelf, thoſe which thou who art a part of me, a Member of my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy giveſt me with thy Blaſphemies, with thy Oaths and Execrations, thoſe are the Wounds that ſtabb me to the heart, that crucifie me afreſh, that put me anew to open ſhame. Pitty it is that thoſe who are right as to their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhould be perverſe in their Wills, and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar in their Affections: That thoſe who are ſo far inlightned in their minds ſhould mix Heaven with Earth, light with Darkneſs, for what Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip or Communion is there between them. Oh! if there be any ſuch here, let me beſeech them by the Mercies of God, by the Bowels of Chriſt Jeſus, not to Eclipſe the Light of their Profeſſion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:63799:8"/>by the dull interpoſition of their carnal and Earthly deſires.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another ſort of the Enemies of the <hi>Church,</hi> which do her and themſelves no ſmall prejudice, are thoſe who by oppoſing her Doctrine, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from her Communion upon ſlight and frivolous pretences, do what in them lyes to looſe thoſe Bands and Ligaments of Order that preſerve her within the Terms and Limits of one entire Body and Society. What Opinion this ſort of People, who out of an over nice and Curious Tenderneſs run from one extreme ſometimes to another have, I know not; but this I think, that no rational unprejudiced perſon can altogether excuſe them from giving Offence, and Scandal to the <hi>Catholick Church of Chriſt,</hi> whereof they either are or ought to be Members. If <hi>Laceration,</hi> if <hi>Diſtortion,</hi> if <hi>Mutilation</hi> bring pain, deformity and imperfection along with them, then ſure I am that thoſe who tear one Member from another, who divide the continuity of Chriſts Myſtical Body, and cut off diverſe from the whole, muſt needs not only ſpoyle the Beauty and Comlineſs of her who is the faireſt of ten Thouſand, but alſo bring torment and vexation, pains and diſeaſes to the great and univerſal Congregation of the Faithful. Theſe unneceſſary, I may ſay scandalous Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:63799:8"/>are as the <hi>Rickets</hi> which hinder the growth of the <hi>Church,</hi> that impair her ſtrength, and make her Limbs knotty and diſproportioned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third, laſt, and moſt dangerous ſort of thoſe who afflict <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſeek her utter ruine and deſtruction that I ſhall mention, are thoſe who either out of Ignorance, or ſecular Carnal ſelf Intereſt, or both, corrupt her Doctrine, and either propoſe new, and unwarrantable Articles of Belief for the Terms of their Communion, and as the neceſſary conditions of Salvation, or elſe detain part of that which is neceſſary to be aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to, and practiced; from the knowledge of thoſe who are ſubject to their Authority, and Miniſterial Juriſdiction. Theſe deliver the Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men inſtead of the Oracles of God, and impoſe uncertain Traditions inſtead of Divine Truths upon the overcredulous and eaſily ſeduced Multitude: God hath commanded the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Stewards of his Church to prepare whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Pottage for the Sons of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> but they who have long, (though upon falſe grounds) pretended to be folely authorized, and commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onated for that Employment have gathered wild <hi>Gourds,</hi> venomous <hi>Colloquintidu</hi> inſtead of favory favory Herbs, ſo that we are forced to cry out that there is Death in the Pot, there is no ſafety
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:63799:9"/>in eating and drinking with them after a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious manner, no Communicating with them in in the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of infection, till ſome <hi>Flour,</hi> which was <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha's</hi> cure of the Deadly Pottage, be acknowleged to be in their <hi>Hoſt;</hi> which they (for Reaſons beſt know to themſelves) will not allow of. They have ſo poyſon'd and Corrupted the pure Streams of Gods Word, which ſhould make glad the Church, which is the City of our God, that he that continueth to drink his fill of thoſe putrified Waters without a ſpecial Antidote dyeth. Nay the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> ſome of the greateſt Empoyſoners, and Sorcerers have turn'd them, as once the River <hi>Nilo</hi> was, into blood; that is by their falſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and miſinterpretations of the Sacred Writ they have extracted bloody and cruel Principles out of it. And by vertue of that unlimited, and uncontroulable Authority they would falſly fetch from thence, aſſume to themſelves a power (which they have but too often uſed) of Dethroming Kings and Princes: and by diſſolving the bands of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> expoſe them to the rage and fury of their own Subjects; impudently denouncing the fatal Sentences of Deprivation and Deſtruction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe Soveraign and Anomted Heads, whoſe Authority is in thoſe Sacred Volumus moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:63799:9"/>plainly aſſerted; and their Perſons moſt expreſſly protected. To paſs by that rabble of <hi>Hereticks</hi> that aroſe in the Primitive Times, (for the good Man had no ſooner Sowne his Wheat but the evil one ſcatter'd his tares amongſt it) the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as infamous now for her Apoſtacy, as ſhe was once Famous for her Faith, hath willfully incurr'd the ſevere penalty mentioned by St. <hi>John</hi> in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> adding to and diminiſhing from the expreſs word of God; nay ſome of her Communion have been ſo impudent as not only to corrupt ſeveral places of the Holy Scriptures, but even to Abaſe the value of that which they have left untainted and untoucht, Preferring their <hi>Canon</hi> Law, before the law of God, preferring the arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray conſtitutions of St. <hi>Peters</hi> pretended Succeſſor to the undoubted and Divinely inſpired writings of St. <hi>Paul:</hi> one inſtance of which I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of their own <hi>Decretalls:</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>Secundam accipere uxorem Secundum Apoſtoli praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum licitum eſt, Secundum vero veritatis rationem verè Fornicatio.</hi> That is as much as to ſay, that according to the word of God in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles Second Marriages are lawfull, but according to the word of God, as they would have it in their <hi>Canon</hi> Law written 1200 years after, 'tis plain For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives a command to <hi>Timothy</hi> to keep ſafe that committed to his Charge, to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:63799:10"/>preſerve the Talent of <hi>Catholick Faith</hi> delivered to him unbroken and uncorupt, neither perverted or crak't in it's order by <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> nor tainted in it's Doctrine by <hi>Haereticks:</hi> but it ſeemes the <hi>Pope</hi> who ſo frequently and ſo eaſily, (though it may be not ſo cheaply) diſpenſed with others, hath given himſelf a Diſpenſation from this Golden Rule: makeing ſuch an unequall Exchange with us, as <hi>Diomedes</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> made with <hi>Glaucas</hi> for his Armour, braſs for Gold: giveing us brazen, impudent, counterfiet Traditions, for the Golden Armour of Gods word which admitts of noe Droſs, no Alloye.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Enemies of the Church are many, ſo are their Aſſaults frequent, their induſtry un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied, and their malice ſtill ragoing, though continually unſucceſsfull. Like Couragious Gamſters, two or three unlucky Games cannot, diſhearten them, nay the more they looſe, the eagerer they are thinking though in vain, that ſome one fortunate hit may make them amends for their former diſappointments, and anſwer their ſo often deluded expectations. It was a great comfort to <hi>Iſrael</hi> that though <hi>Siſera</hi> had nine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Chariots of Iron, and a vaſt Army with which he haraſt and oppreſt them for twenty years, that yet one overthrow given him by <hi>Deborah</hi> ſecured them from all ſuch hoſtile Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:63799:10"/>for a long time after: But here it is as with the <hi>Hydra,</hi> out off one head and two ſprings up in the place of it: Though divers of the heads of the adverſaries of <hi>Sion</hi> have been fixt on Poles for their Treachery and Rebellion, to be a terror and warning to others to avoyd the ſame indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Courſes, leaſt they meet with the ſame fatall end, yet there have been alwayes other Heads of the ſame Mould, and Figure, and are ſtill buſily plotting, and contriveing the downfall, and ruine of this poor Church of <hi>England,</hi> forſaken of thoſe who ſhould be her Friends, and expoſed to thoſe adverſaries whoſe Deſignes is to Swallow both. And no wonder it is that theſe fiery Exhalations continue burning in their Malice for ſo many Ages together, ſeeing they have a plentifull Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of unctuous, and Sulphureous matter from Hell it ſelf which maintains the flames of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which like the Funerall pile of the two irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable Brothers, <hi>Eteoches,</hi> and <hi>Polmices</hi> whoſe Enmity laſted longer then their breath, divide themſelves, as alſo the more vehement fire of Perſecution.</p>
            <p>The Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> are moved by a reſtleſs Spirit, even by him who is ever in action going too and fro about the Earth: and his chief buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and deſigne is to diſturb the Peace of <hi>Sion</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:63799:11"/>and to hinder the wellfare of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> to pull down the old Temple of the Lord and to erect a new Chappel for his own Worſhip. From the infancy of Religion he began to perſecute the holy Seed nor will he leave off to malign their happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to create them trouble till this world be no more, and till they arrive at that unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able State of reſt, and Security, which he being bound with his confederates in everlaſting chains of darkneſs ſhall have no power though his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe will ſhall ſtill be the ſame, to deſturb or moleſt. he ſeduced <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Paradice</hi> from the duty She owed to her Lord and Husband, and drew both of them from their Allegiance to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Head and Maſter: and thereby made them inſtrumentall to their own and our Miſery: He inſtigated <hi>Cain</hi> to Sacrifice his innocent Brother, indeavouring thereby to deſtroy the Church in the firſt Marter and Confeſſor of it. Endleſs would it be, and indeed needleſs to run through the many oppoſitions that the choſen People of God met with by his ſly, and cunning inſinuations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their ſettlement in the promis'd Land: need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I ſay it would be to rehearſe the ſeverall hardſhips they underwent, in a Congregation of reformed <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to whom the free uſe of the Sacred Hiſtory of the <hi>Bible</hi> is allowed in their own tongue, wherein the ſeveral particulars re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:63799:11"/>thereunto are contained. Were I indeed to Preach to an Aſſembly of Lay <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and had occaſion to make uſe of any part of the Sacred writ, to give a demonſtration of Gods care of his People under their moſt cruel and ſevere Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, then it would be neceſſary to make a full, and perfect recitall of all the circumſtances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to ſuch a deliverance; and that becauſe their cunning and mercileſs Spiritual Guides as they call them, look up the Records of <hi>Eternal Truth</hi> from them, and keep them in ignorance of thoſe wonderfull works of God which he hath done for his choſen Seed: it being in ſome of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Countryes as they are Stiled, a crime within the compaſs of the Inquiſtion for any laick to have a <hi>Bible</hi> in the Vulgar tongue in his cuſtody: but to you it is given to know thoſe truths that concern your everlaſting Salvation; and if it be not your own or your Parents faults you may be able to underſtand the whole Series, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Gods Mercies to his Church from the beginning of the world till the Revelation of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Happy are you if you know how to make a right uſe of this great Priviledge to your own advantage: I ſhall therefore be very brief, and that rather to refreſh your Memories, then to inform your underſtandings. I ſhall not ſtand to reckon up the ſeveral <hi>Depravations, Schiſmes,</hi> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:63799:12"/>perſecutions that hapened to the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under the ſeveral Diſpenſations of the Old Law untill the comeing of our Saviour in the fleſh: and then at the Entrance of the Captain of our Salvation on the great, and charitable work of our Redemption, Satan renews his Aſſaults, doubles his files, and again ſeeks to ſtrangle Chriſtianity in the very Cradle. He incites <hi>Herod</hi> to lay in wait for him, and what he could not accompliſh by his Agents he attempts to perform in his own Perſon, after this he expoſes him to the malice of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> and at laſt when he thought his deſigne finiſht, he was vanquiſht by the Croſs, and the Death of <hi>Jeſus</hi> prov'd the life of his Church: who knows not what Enemies, how powerfull, and how cruel the firſt Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gators of the Chriſtian Religion met with from his bloody Inſtruments in the firſt Ages, and Centuries of the Church? how they were thrown to wild Beaſts, devoted to the flames, Broyl'd upon Gridireons, pounded in Mortars, and put to all the Torments that Mans malicious wit could invent, or his power execute: Afterwards when the Goſpel of Grace, and Peace, had by its own inocent Arts and ireſiſtable Charmes, (the Divine Spirit working along with them) ſpread it ſelf over a great part of the world, but then by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees (as the beſt things here below are ſubiect
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:63799:12"/>to coruption) became tainted with Errors, and overcaſt with Ignorance, and ſuperſtition, when a few (as moſt great things have ſmall beginnings) to whom a light from above ſhined through the groſſe and thick Miſt, being ſenſible of their Errors, and willing to Forſake them, and to bring others likewiſe out of them, Endeavoured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme thoſe dangerous, and damnable Corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions which had (dureing that General ſtate of darkneſs) crept into the Church; what oppoſition? what contradction? what Perſicution? did thoſe firſt Reformers, and Aſſertors of the true Antient Catholick and Apoſtolick-Faith meet with from thoſe whom either incorrigible Obſtinacy cauſed to perſevere in their ignorance; or whom carnall Intereſt obliged to act contrary to thoſe Principles of light, and Knowledge where with they were informed. I might run this from the beginning of our own Reformation down to theſe very days, and ſhow you how the ſeveral Enemies of the Church have been ſtill hammer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beating out Plots, and makeing Fetters from time to time to Shackle us again, and to reduce us to our former Slavery. No ſooner had we through Gods providence eſcaped from the land of Darkneſs but the <hi>Egyptians</hi> as loth to looſe ſo ſweet and profitable a pray purſued us, uſeing all Arts, and means both force, and cunning, both
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:63799:13"/>threatings, and temptations to bring us back to our old houſe of Bondage: But this will more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly belong to the third head: which was this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> are many, and their Aſſaults frequent, ſo they have many ways to accompliſh, and bring about their Pernitious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes. They know that the ſame Stratagems in Warr are ſeldom twice us'd with good ſucceſs: and therefore they vary their Arts, and change their Habits according to the times they live in, and the Perſons with whom they have to deal. I might ſhow you here what little and yet deſtructive Arts ſome of the Enemies of our Church breed amongſt our ſelves (doubtleſs deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veing their ſmall bye Streames from the corrupt and infected Fountain of <hi>Rome</hi>) uſe to under mine her Foundations, and by diſſolveing her Order endeavouring to ſubvert her very Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution. But ſeeing the ſolemnity of this day, the happy day of our Deliverance from one of the moſt horid Plots that ever was contriv'd againſt our Religion, and juſt upon the Brinke of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, ſeems to Point to me to direct my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to that Party who were the cruel Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Abettors of that helliſh Conſpiracy, I ſhall wave thoſe leſſor Diſturbers of our peace, and come to that open, and profeſſed Enemy of our Religion as by Law Eſtabliſht amongſt us:
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:63799:13"/>Following the method that <hi>Gregory Nazianzone</hi> does in his firſt Invective againſt <hi>Julian,</hi> who would not medle, as he tells us in the beginning of his Declamation, with <hi>Sehon</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> nor with <hi>Og</hi> King of <hi>Baſan,</hi> ſmall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable Princes; and who only endamag'd a little part of the Church <hi>Iſrael:</hi> but that he would direct his Arrows againſt that great Proud Spirit, that Dragon, that Apoſtate, that common Enemy, and diſturber of Mankind. we will at preſent paſs by thoſe who do not Practice what they profeſs, though they are a great Diſhonour to our Church; we will ſlip over in ſilence thoſe who though in moſt Points they acknowledge her Doctrine, doe yet without any real grounds diſſent from her Diſcipline, though this be an unknown injury and diſcredit to her, and as great an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to themſelves, and come to this great Monſter this red Dragon, red with the blood of the Saints, to this ungratefull Backſlider of <hi>Rome</hi> who brings a diſreputation on that once Famous Place where the Apoſtles of the Gentiles, and the great Miniſter of the Circumciſion Preacht up that pure and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere word of Truth, which is their at this time, and hath been for ſome ages ſo abominable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterated, and corrupted: <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave St. <hi>Peter</hi> the Keys and commanded him to lay aſide his Sword, but his pretended Succeſſor hath beaten
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:63799:14"/>them into two Swords a Temporall, and a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, with both which he Tyranizeth over the Kings and Princes of the Earth, witneſs thoſe Emperors he hath Excommunicated with the one, that ſo he might the ſooner, and eaſier diſpatch them with the other.</p>
            <p>Should I recite the ſeveral Murders, and Maſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acres that the feirce Propugnators of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> intereſt have committed, that deluge of the blood of the <hi>Saints</hi> which they have ſpilt and the cruel and Barbarous torments they have expoſed them to, my Sermon muſt become a Martyrology, and theſe few Papers ſwell into a Volume: all Hiſtory that runs parallel with their <hi>Epoche</hi> abounds with inſtances of their cruelty and violence: Neither are their own writers ſhye in relateing the great Slaughters they, have made, and the many out rages they have committed for the propagation of their Religion, and the rooteing this peſtilent <hi>Northeren Hereſie</hi> of ours as they call it out of the world: glorying in their Villanies when Growned with Victory and triumph, but diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them when <hi>Abortive</hi> and unſucceſsfull. And if this barefaced, and open way of proceeding will not ſerve their turns; if plain force will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, then in the next place they have recourſe to hidden Arts, and ſecret Treachery: what they cannot compaſs in the open field, they endeavour to effect by Ambuſh, by drawing thoſe lives
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:63799:14"/>they aime at into a ſnare under the pretence of a Treaty for accommodation: witneſs <hi>John Huſſe,</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> both betray'd by the Emperours Letters of ſafe conduct into their Enemies hands, and then Sacrificed to their Zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fury: ſo unſafe is it to put any confidence in them whoſe Sacred Principle it is not to keep their promiſe with them whom they are pleas'd to brand with the title of <hi>Haereticks.</hi> But more eſpecially for ever be remembred the barbarous, and inhumane Maſſacre at <hi>Paris</hi> whither the chief of the Proteſtant party were decoy'd under the pretence of an accord, and there miſerably Butcher'd. Sometimes they work under ground ſhowing themſelves thereby the Children of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they conceal their intentions the better to bring them to perfection: We ought to bleſs God dayly for the many Seaſonable Deliverances He hath at all times afforded us from the many Treacherous Deſignes which that reſtleſs party have contrived againſt the Perſons of our <hi>Princes,</hi> and the Body of our Religion: but more particularly we have, as we ought, this Morning offer'd up the unbloudie Sacrifice of our Praiſe and thanksgiveing in the name and the ſence of our Church to our gratious and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Preſerver for the timely and happy diſcovery of that <hi>Powder Plot</hi> which was hatcht in Hell,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:63799:15"/>wrought in darkneſs, and ſhould have been this Day executed in Clouds, and Pillars of Smoke: A Smoke like that which aroſe out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit, like the ſmoke of a Furnace; a ſmoke which would have Eclips'd our Sun and Moone; our King, and Prince: that would, have dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Stars of the firſt Magnitude our Nobles; as likewiſe the leſſer Conſtellations, the lower houſe of Parliament: and which is more, and which, had been worſe (though all was bad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) a Smoke which had quite put out the Glorious Light of the Goſpell, the very Eye, and Sight of this our moſt excellently Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: and a ſmoke at laſt which like that aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending from the infernal Pit, would have brought whole ſwarmes of Locuſts, and Caterpillers, of Monks, and Fryers, of Prieſts and Jeſuits, which would have devoured all that had been green, and pleaſant, all that had been pure, and wholſome in this our fruitful Land, through this fire (for their is no ſmoke but hath ſome fire) they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have Sacrificed our Conſciences to the <hi>Moloch</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> that cruell Idol that kills ſooneſt thoſe whome it embraces cloſeſt.</p>
            <p>I need not give you a Reſation of that wicked and pernicious deſigne; their late Practiſes, and contrivances to overturn the Foundation of our Religion hath ſufficiently revived the memory
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:63799:15"/>of their ancient deteſtable conſpiracies, and of this unparalleld one among the reſt; ſo that now almoſt every Child is made acquainted with it, and the Fathers ſhall teach their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſays upon the like occaſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 78, 4.5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>that their Poſterity may know it, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that are yet unborn, to the intent that when they came up they might ſhew their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the ſome &amp;c.</hi> and therefore I ſhall paſs on to ſomething elſe. Theſe ways they have to offend their Enemies, other ways they have to gain Friends and to obtain <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> one way is by ſpeaking them fair with large Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes of Indulgence and Preferment: how many hath the hope of Liberty to do what they pleaſe upon eaſy termes of Abſolution Seduced from the Truth, and caus'd them to make Shipwrack of their Fayth? And as they have this way to gain them ſo they have another to retaine them: falſe ſignes, lyeing wonders, and counterfiet Miracles: for certainly as the deluſions of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sorcerers were in ſome meaſure a cauſe why <hi>Pharouh</hi> was more perverſe, and his heart more hardned againſt the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo the ſtrong opinion that the vulgar have of the reality of thoſe ſignes and wonders that are pretended to be wrought amongſt them is a great reaſon of the continuation of their Spirituall
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:63799:16"/>Captivity. Theſe wayes and ſeveral, others they have to promote their cauſe, and make their worſe then <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sorceryes to prevaile but to no purpoſe, for there is one in Heaven that laughs them to ſcorne; for as <hi>Balaam</hi> when Divinely inſpired ſaid:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 23.23.</note> Surely there is no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantment againſt <hi>Jacob;</hi> neither is their any Divination againſt <hi>Iſrael:</hi> according to this time ſhall it be ſayd of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> what hath God wrought? which makes good the next <hi>General</hi> I am to ſpeak to which muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to all good men.</p>
            <p>The Fruſtration of their deſigne: or the ill ſucceſs which they meet with, that ſtrive to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Truth by violence, or detain it in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs by fraud: yet have they not prevailed againſt me.</p>
            <p>Many are the inventions of the wicked, many their Plots and Stratagems, many their devices, and ſubtle Machinations, but the Counſel of the Lord that ſhall ſtand! As Satan and his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are reſtleſs Perſecutors of the Saints; ſo is God a ſure reſcuer, and Preſerver of them: Though the red Dragon call together all his infernall Legions;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.7.</note> all the Principalities, and Powers of darkneſs, all the numerous hoſt of the bottomleſs Pit; yet the victory ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main with <hi>Michael:</hi> for indeed it is <hi>Imper con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſus,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:63799:16"/>a very unequall Match? for although the Devil in Scripture be ſtiled the ſtrong one, yet hath he to deal with a ſtronger then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, with one who can when he pleaſes reſtrain his fury, and dispoſſeſſe him of all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous Holds he hath gotten) and diſappoint him and his Agents of their moſt forward and pregnant hopes even upon the Edge, and point of their accompliſhment. As the Enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> have many wayes, and many meanes to afflict her, ſo God hath many ways, and many means to protect and defend her. I cannot ſhow all the ways, and Methods which our Almighty Preſerver makes uſe of to ſave and deliver his Choſen, becauſe many of the Paths of his ſecret Providence are unknown to us, and paſt finding out: neither can I inſiſt long upon thoſe ſeveral wayes, that are diſcovered to us in holy writ, which his divine wiſdom uſes for their contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall Preſervation: I ſhall inſtance in the two moſt comprehenſive Methods I can think of and be as brief in them as I can.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſpeciall Providence of God is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ſhown in the ſingular Protection of his Servants from thoſe dangers that ariſe from neceſſary cauſes, from ſuch as act from their naturall inclinations, or at leaſt ways without much premeditation or deſigne.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:63799:17"/>
            <p n="2">2. His infinite Love to his People is more Eminently diſcovered in the various Methods he takes to ſecure them from the miſchiefs that are deſign'd them by voluntary Agents. But before I treate of either of theſe I muſt premiſe this by way of caution; That God does not allways make uſe of any peculiar providence for the preſervation of his deareſt Children either from dangers ariſeing from neceſſary, or free Agents, and therefore we are not raſhly to judge of all thoſe who come to any Misfortune either from the one, or the other Cauſe. Sometimes he ſuffers his cheifeſt Favourits to be ſawn aſunder, to paſs through the flames, and thoſe of whom the world was not worthy to be ſtoned, and ſlain with the Sword, here in ſuffering the Malice of the wicked for ſome private end of his own to take it's naturall courſe, and to obtain it's deſigned Purpoſe; ſometimes likewiſe he ſuffers his own Children to come to ſudden, and as we call them untimely Ends; by ſome unforeſeen, and therefore unavoideable accident: but chiefely and generally ſpeaking God as I ſhall ſhow you is pleas'd to give ſignall Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his particular care of his own People, in preſerveing them from the many fatall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers they are ſubiect to from the one and the many bloudy contrivances that threaten them from the other Cauſe.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:63799:17"/>
            <p n="1">1 Gods care is remarkeable in the preſervation of his Servants from dangers ariſeing from naturall Cauſes: He oftentimes for the Safeguard and Protection of his People either reſtraines the violence and Malignity of them, or elſe alters, or ſuſpends their Property: Thus he reſtrain'd the conſumeing nature of the fire in the over heat Furnace into which the three-Children, (the bold oppoſers of <hi>Jdolatry</hi> to the Kings face) were caſt, So that they walked unconcernedly in it, as though they had only been ſurrounded with a harmleſs <hi>Lambent</hi> flame. Thus the viper that faſtned on St. <hi>Pauls</hi> hand by the wonderfull Providence of God, (whoſe firſt motions all natural Agents muſt needs obey) had loſt its innate venome, which was turned into an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent juyce: and this is one of the promiſes which our bleſſed Saviour made, to his Diſciples a little before his Aſcention mentioned by St <hi>Marke:</hi> They ſhall take up Serpents,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.18.</note> and if they drink any deadly thing it ſhall not hurt them. we are told by <hi>Job</hi> that the ſtones of the feild ſhall be in League with the <hi>Righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 5.27.</note> and that the beaſts of the field ſhould be at peace with him. Thus God ſhut the Mouths of the Lyons, and took away their ravenous appetite, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his Servant <hi>Daniell,</hi> whoſe onely crime was his Devotion, his not dareing to offer up
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:63799:18"/>any Petition but to his God only. and we know that the ſtones which the people of <hi>Lyſtra</hi> (the ſame perſons whome St <hi>Paul</hi> had lately before Reſtrain'd with much adoe from <hi>Idolatry.</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> 14.19.</note> threw at that great <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> were more favourable to him then the hard hearts of the misguided rabble; Thus the fire ſhall not burn, nor the viper ſting, nor the Lyons devour, nor the ſtones kill, nor the Oyle Scald, (St <hi>Johns</hi> deliverance at <hi>Patmos</hi>) when God is pleaſed to appear for the ſecurity and Preſervation of thoſe who ſtand up in oppoſition to <hi>Idolatry</hi> and Superſtition in defence of his own true worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſpeciall Providence of God is moſt Eminently diſcovered in the ſeverall methods he takes to ſecure them from the violence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended them by voluntary Agents. And this God does ſometimes by turning the hearts or thoſe who wiſh evil unto <hi>Sion</hi> into a friendly compliance with her. thus he protected his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Iacob</hi> twice in the ſame journey, when <hi>Laban</hi> purſued him, and his incenſed Brother <hi>Eſau</hi> went forth to meet him. Sometimes by turning the fury and violence of the enemies upon themſelves: Thus the warr between the <hi>Turks,</hi> and the <hi>Perſian</hi> was for a long time the Safeguard, and preſervation of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in <hi>Hungary:</hi> and often times the jealouſies
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:63799:18"/>and conteſts amongſt the ſeveral Sects of the <hi>Mahometans</hi> have diverted the arms of thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidells, or recalled them from the advantages they had gained by their vaſt multitudes: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God is pleas'd to ſend Panick fears, and general conſternations amongſt the Enemies of <hi>Sion,</hi> thereby making them afraid of their own ſhadows, and cauſeing them to fly when there is none to purſue.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kings</hi> 2 <hi>book</hi> 7.6.</note> Thus he made the <hi>Syrians</hi> to here the noiſe of Chariots and Horſes, even as the noiſe of a great hoſt, and they aroſe and fled, and left all their Furniture and proviſion behind them to the great comfort of the allmoſt ſtarved <hi>Samaritans.</hi> At other times he preſerves his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants by diſcovering the councills, and revealing the deſignes of thoſe that ſeek their deſtruction: thus God by the Prophet <hi>Eliſha</hi> diſcovered the ſecret Cabinet Councills of the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> by which means the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaved himſelf: otherwhile he ſmites them with blindneſs, as he did he great hoſt that came to intrap the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eliſha</hi> and takes them in the ſame ſnare they layd for others. Sometimes he infatuates their Councills, makeing them thereby inſtrumentall to the preſervation of thoſe whom they had markt out for deſtruction: Thus the writeing of an ambiguous Letter to the Lord <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eagle</hi> to diſwade him from coming to the Houſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:63799:19"/>that day was a Secondary means of preventing that bloody, and horid deſigne which ſhould on this day have been executed, and for the happy diſcovery whereof we have this Morning paid our gratefull acknowledgment to our Mercifull Saviour and Deliverer.</p>
            <p>And as God hath many ways ſo he hath many means to protect his Choſen, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs either the force or to defeat the cunning of their Adverſaries: As his Angels, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Spirits ſent abroad continually for the good of his Elect: witneſs <hi>Sonacheribs</hi> vaſt army deſtroyd in one night by them: his Magiſtrates which are the Sheilds of the Earth, and his Miniſters which are the Chariots and horſemen of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But in all theſe we muſt look up to God, the firſt Mover of the wheel and return our Praiſe and thankſgiveing to him, to whom it alone belongs, which brings me to the laſt head The duty of the Church; the thankfull retribution ſhe is bound to make to her great Champion, and Defender of all her deliverances: <hi>may Iſrael now ſay.</hi> The remembrance of her paſt dangers ought to be the Burden of her Song of thankſgiving: as the Reduplication in the Text, and in other places of the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> ſeem to import <hi>Not unto us, not unto us O Lord but unto thy Name be glory; they compaſſed me
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:63799:19"/>about, they compaſſed me I ſay about, but in the Name of the Lord I will deſtroy them.</hi> All the redoublings almoſt that we meet with are but ſo many repetitions of Gods favour, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, whereby we are the more effectually and ſtrongly ſtird up to a chearfull thankfullneſs to him who is the Giver of all victory and the only Preſerver of all thoſe that fear him, and put their truſt in his mercy.</p>
            <p>A gratefull acknowledgment of Benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived is one of the firſt Principles and common notions we bring into the world along with us: neither have we only the indelible and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſible Law of Nature to commend this duty of gratitude to us, but the poſitive command of God himſelf to inforce the commemoration of either particular or national deliverances, under no leſs apenalty then the abſolute forfeiture of them: God will by no means admit that his mercies ſhould be writ in Sand to be waſht away by the next coming in of the Tyde; but that they ſhould be recorded in ſuch laſting Characters that may tranſmit them to ſucceeding genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. He commanded a Pot of <hi>Manna</hi> to be preſerved in his Tabernacle to teſtifie to after ages that miraculous Providence where by he ſuſtained the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for forty years in the dry and barren Wilderneſs: And when
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:63799:20"/>the waters of <hi>Jordan</hi> were dryd up to afford an eaſie paſſage to that vaſt army into the promis'd Land, we find that <hi>Joſhua</hi> erected 12 ſtones in the place where the waters were cut off, to be a perpetuall Memoriall of that wonderous ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Nay we are told that in the ſame place where they paſt over the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> the Print, and Footſteps of that Stupendious March. May be ſeen to this day, as a laſting Monument of that Miraculous Preſervation: I ſhall not ſtand to juſtifie the truth of that bold and ſeemingly improbable relation; but ſure I am that the ſignall ſteps, and prints of this days wonderfull deliverance remain freſh in this Nation to this preſent time, for though many noble, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent neighbouring Structures have ſince (not without ſuſpition of indirect contrivances from the ſame cruell hands) felt the fury of the mercileſs Flames: yet thoſe ancient, and glorious Piles of building at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where the Plot was layd, where the ſeene was contrived, and which were deſigned, for one common heap of rubiſh, ſtand hitherto as a monument of our Churches triumph, and their ſhame, and at once bid defiance to the jaws of Time, and their inveterate Malice.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:63799:20"/>
            <p>Let not therefore the complicated Bleſſings which by the happy diſcovery of this days horrid Treaſons deſcended upon this Nation be blotted out of our remembrance ſo long as we wiſh well to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarchy or to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> for to this days <hi>Triumph we owe the Preſervation of both.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay leaſt the remembrance of thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Deliverances that God hath beſtowed upon this Kingdome by ſnatching it out of the bloody Jaws of <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould ever be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by us; he hath been gratiouſly pleas'd, as it were to refreſh our Memoryes, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print the Characters of his goodneſs to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to our Poſterity, to ſignalize once more the ſame day of the ſame Month, and the ſame date of the year with freſh inſtances of his gratious Providence over us, and his ſingular protection of us, and our moſt excellent Religion. Mikeing 88 in this wonderfull Century, and the now twice happy fifth of <hi>November,</hi> (the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous day of his preſent Sacred Majeſties Arrivall in <hi>England,</hi> for the Preſervation of our Liberties and Religion) the joyfull Seaſons once more of our deliverance from that fearfull inundation of <hi>Popery</hi> that was ready to break in upon us.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:63799:21"/>
            <p>Let us therefore offer unto God our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and Preſerver a double Tribute of thankfullneſs for the joynt Deliverances vouch ſaf'd to us, and our fore Fathers on this Solemn Feſtivall, which deſerves to be mark't with a new Star, and colour'd with a freſh, and richer graine in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Calender.</p>
            <p>Deliverances by which we are reſcued from being carried back to our old abandond <hi>Egypt</hi> of Idolatry, and Superſtition. Mercies to which we owe the continuance of many noble Families which otherwiſe had been blown up without any Luxury or Prodigality of their own: and laſtly Mercies to which we muſt aſcribe the free Excerciſe of our Religion, and our meeting together in this venerable, and Aguſt Place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for Gods holy Worſhip; (a place to which that Party were lately too near Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and which they lookt upon with too greedy an Eye) whereby we have this opper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Magnifieing that gratious Providence which countermind all their helliſh Plots in both the Miraculous Revolutions.</p>
            <p>And ſet us ſhow our Gratitude to Almighty God on this great occaſion chiefly by wiſhing well unto <hi>Sion,</hi> and doing the things that may conduce to her Peace.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:63799:21"/>
            <p>Let us not be acceſſory to our own Misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes in calling down judgements from Heaven, in removeing thoſe Golden Candleſticks which are yet, God be praiſed, (and long may they continue ſo) fixt in our Sanctuaries either by the wickedneſs of our lives, or the vitiouſneſs of our Principles. Let there be no Diviſions among us, the fomenting of which is the ready way to blaſt, and ſully thoſe extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary bleſſings which we at preſent enjoy; and which an unanimous conformity to the moſt pure and excellent rules and Diſcipline of our Church, is the moſt likely, and prudentiall way to confirme to our further Benefit, and advantage. Let thoſe who upon ſlight, and triviall Grounds ſeparate from our Communion conſider ſeriouſly with themſelves, who they were, that have ever ſince the Reformation been the ſtout oppoſers of <hi>Popery,</hi> and who they now are which appear as the reſolute Champions of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion againſt all it's Enemies whatſoever. And then let them be aſham'd to ſtand out any longer againſt them, who have alwayes ſtood in the Gap to Defend them, and the Faith which they Profeſs.</p>
            <p>Let them all run into the Arms of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and reſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:63799:22"/>aſſured that they cannot but be ſafe unde her Shelter whom God hath ſo miraculouſly reſtored, and preſerved: And let all acquieſce in the wiſe, and the ſober determinations of thoſe Reverend, and pious Compilers of the moſt excellent form of her <hi>Dicipline</hi> which as well as her <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſome of them ſeald, and confirm'd with their beſt blood. For we may aſſure our ſelves of this Truth, that as a Church over burden'd with a multitude of <hi>Ceremonies</hi> is like a Bird with great Wings, many gay Feathers, and a ſmall light, empty uſeleſs Body; So that Church (if we may call it one) that deſpiſes all outward Decency, and Order, is like the unplum'd <hi>Jay</hi> in the Fable, a trouble to her ſelf, and laughing ſtock to her Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Laſtly let us endeavour to be Sober in our Judgements, prudent in our Converſation; putting on a calme, meek, obedient, teachable Temper; not affecting ſingularity, but agreeing as in one Faith, one Hope, one Baptiſme, in the acknowledgement of one Lord, and Saviour of us all: So likewiſe in one outward form of worſhip, even that Incomperable one which is ſo happily (and long may it be ſo) Eſtabliſh't by Law among us.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:63799:22"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And let Us, bleſs and Praiſe God for all his Mercies; and then God ſhall bleſs us, and continue this moſt excellent Religion which we profeſs, and enjoy, in ſpight of all it's Adverſaries, and Oppoſers whatſoever, to us, and our Poſterity for many and many Generations; till all Churches ſhall be gathered into one, and united to their Supreme head Chriſt Jeſus our bleſſed Saviour, and Deliverer, to whome with the Father, and the Holy Spirit, three Perſons, and one God be aſcribed oll Power, Praiſe, Honour, and Glory for ever and ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
